¬
{SACK_PLAYER_BODY}Grave tidings my Lord! Our camp got sacked!\n\nThere's no single golden plate left to feast on.\nWe'll take revenge on our foes one day!
{SACK_PLAYER_TITLE}Camp sacked!
{SACK_AI_BODY}Great tidings my Lord! Our soldiers sacked the enemy camp!\n\nThis additional income will ease the pain of loosing our men in battle.\nNow, let us pray for more victories in the battles ahead of us.
{SACK_AI_TITLE}Enemy camp sacked!
{AMERICA_DISCOVERED_BODY}Testing the theory that one can head east by sailing west carried the risk of a remote, watery grave. Yet this act of courage has been rewarded with the discovery of a strange new land... perchance a whole new world. Who knows what riches await those with the courage to explore.
{AMERICA_DISCOVERED_TITLE}New World Discovered
{AL_IDRISI_BODY}Abu Abd Allah Muhammad al-Idrisi, the Moroccan cartographer, geographer and traveller who lived in Sicily, at the court of King Roger II, has died. His best known work is his map of the world 'lawh al-tarsim' (plank of draught), or 'Tabula Rogeriana', of 1154. This work will be the standard volume for centuries to come. Roger II of Sicily has had his world map drawn on a circle of silver weighing about 400 pounds along with a world globe of 400 kg pure silver which al-Idrisi constructed, which precisely records all trade routes, lakes and rivers, major cities, plains and mountains.
{AL_IDRISI_TITLE}Abu Abd Allah Muhammad al-Idrisi dies
{ALBERTUS_MAGNUS_BODY}Grave tidings, the Dominican friar and venerated scholar Albertus Magnus has died. He was the greatest German scholar of our age, honoured by all, granted the rare title of Doctor of the Church, first to apply Aristotle’s philosophy to Christian thought and a staunch advocate for the peaceful coexistence of science and religion.. He will be sorely missed.
{ALBERTUS_MAGNUS_TITLE}Albertus Magnus dies
{ANNA_COMNENA_BODY}Born December 1, 1083, eldest of nine children. Trained in the study of history, mathematics, science, and Greek philosophy, this woman is perhaps the world's first female historian and is a major source of information about the reign of her father, Alexius I. Her 15 volume work, started at the age of 55 while in a monastery, is full of details about daily life at court, the deeds of her family, and the exchanges between the Byzantines and western crusaders during the first crusades.
{ANNA_COMNENA_TITLE}Anna Comnena dies
{ARAGON_KING_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late Aragonese ruler, his heir has succeeded to the throne. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...	
{ARAGON_KING_EVENT_TITLE}The King of Aragon is dead!	
{ARAGON_REGENT_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late Aragonese ruler, a regent has been selected to administer the realm. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...	
{ARAGON_REGENT_EVENT_TITLE}End of a Dynasty?	
{ARTESIAN_WELL_BODY}This first artesian well has been dug by the Carthusian monks in the town of Artois, France, so giving them there name. The technique uses percussion drilling in which a rod with a hard iron cutting edge is placed in the bore hole and repeatedly struck with a hammer, penetrating strata impermeable to water, and so reaching a lower layer of strata containing water under pressure. The water then rises in the bore hole and flows spontaneously out of it.
{ARTESIAN_WELL_TITLE}First Artesian well dug
{ASSASSINS_BODY}A highly devout Ismaili sect leader, Hasan ibn-al-Sabbah, has taken control of the mountain fortress of Alamut for the al-Da'wa al-Jadida sect. To do this Hassan offered 3000 gold dinars to the fort owner for the amount of land that would fit a buffalo’s hide. The term having been agreed upon, Hassan then cut the hide in to strips and joined them all over along the perimeter of the fort. The fort has become known amongst the locals as al-Assas 'the foundation', and its followers as al-Assasin. They are mainly opposed to the Sunni sect, but are also known as Hashshashin or Assassins and their services can be purchase for non religious reasons.
{ASSASSINS_TITLE}A New Deadly Sect 
{BATTLE_HATTIN_BODY}A force of Frankish Nobles, Templars and Hospitallers was destroyed by Saladin at the Horns of Hattin. Saladin followed up the battle with a massacre of over 100 Templars and Hospitallers.
{BATTLE_HATTIN_TITLE}The Battle of Hattin
{BLACK_DEATH_1_BODY}The dire plague that scholars have now dubbed 'The Great Mortality' is continuing its destructive trail through the west. Is the end truly nigh? Is this our judgement, and has the almighty finally decided that we are all too wretched to live?!
{BLACK_DEATH_1_TITLE}The Great Mortality
{BLACK_DEATH_2_BODY}Life in the civilised world has become more morbid and bleak than in known history. Every man woman and child is accustomed to the sight of their people stacked in piles before being burned... In the vain hope that the fires may cleanse this foul doom from the land.\n\nAlthough not everyone is falling victim to its deadly embrace, the plague is still decimating the population everywhere it travels.
{BLACK_DEATH_2_TITLE}The Great Mortality Spreads
{BLACK_DEATH_3_BODY}While the lands that were first stricken by the Great Mortality are beginning to discover a life beyond the plague, many places that had been spared this doom are now feeling its full effects.\n\nThough talk of this truly being the end is becoming less likely with enough survivors to prove the point, this creeping doom is still the most feared thing to stalk the lands of Europe for even the bravest of men, being dubbed "The Black Death" these days.
{BLACK_DEATH_3_TITLE}The Great Mortality Continues
{BLACK_DEATH_4_BODY}It would appear that the Black Death has worked most of its deadly misery upon the world, and that men of all faiths may have reason to make a prayer of thanks... We have been delivered!\n\nAside from some unfortunate destinations at the end of the major trade routes where the plague is a more recent tyrant, the risk of contracting the Black Death appears to now be negligible. Now those who rule the survivors may struggle over what remains of civilisation.
{BLACK_DEATH_4_TITLE}The Black Death Passes
{BLACK_DEATH_HITS_BODY}A plague of unfathomable proportions has made its way westward from the Far East, where it is said to have already ended an untold number of lives. The victims find their skin covered in dark blotches, as they enter a terrible fever and sickness which ultimately leads to a painful and miserable death.\n\nWhile scholars, theologians and physicians cannot agree on the exact cause of this deadly plague, the threat it poses men of all faiths is plain for all to see.
{BLACK_DEATH_HITS_TITLE}A Most Dreaded Plague
{BOLOGNA_UNIVERSITY_BODY}The University of Bologna is the first university founded in the western world, its motto is "Alma mater studiorum" (Latin for "fostering mother of studies"). Masters of grammar, rhetoric and logic begin to devote themselves to the law.
{BOLOGNA_UNIVERSITY_TITLE}University of Bologna founded
{BURNED_STAKE_BODY}The vile heretic Basil the Physician, a leader of the Bulgarian Gnostic Bogomil sect, has been burned to death by order of the Byzantine Emperor for having tried to convert him.
{BURNED_STAKE_TITLE}A Heretic Burned!
{BYZANTIUM_KING_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late Byzantine ruler, his heir has succeeded to the throne. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...	
{BYZANTIUM_KING_EVENT_TITLE}The Byzantine Emperor is dead!	
{BYZANTIUM_REGENT_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late Byzantine ruler, a regent has been selected to administer the realm. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...	
{BYZANTIUM_REGENT_EVENT_TITLE}End of a Dynasty?	
{CHILDRENS_CRUSADE_BODY}Two young boys who claim to have had visions of Jesus, in which he assured them that only the innocence of children will defeat the Saracens, have led a crusade of children to the Holy Lands. Unfortunately, most of these innocent pilgrims have been either lost at sea to storms and rocks, or captured by pirates and slavers.	
{CHILDRENS_CRUSADE_TITLE}Children's Crusade	
{CISTERCIAN_ORDER_BODY}	The first Cistercian abbey is founded by Robert of Molesme in this year of our lord 1098, at Cîteaux Abbey. Known as 'White Monks' because of the colour of the habit they wear, the Cistercian's seek to return to a literal observance of the Rule of St Benedict, rejecting the developments the Benedictines have undergone. They try to reproduce life exactly as it was in Saint Benedict's time, with a return to manual labour, especially to field-work, a special characteristic of Cistercian life. 
{CISTERCIAN_ORDER_TITLE}Cistercian Order founded
{CUMANS_KING_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late Cuman ruler, his heir has succeeded to the throne. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...	
{CUMANS_KING_EVENT_TITLE}The Cuman Khan is dead!	
{CUMANS_REGENT_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late Cuamn ruler, a regent has been selected to administer the realm. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...	
{CUMANS_REGENT_EVENT_TITLE}End of a Dynasty?	
{COUNCIL_OF_CLERMONT_BODY}The Council of Clermont takes place. On the last day of the council Pope Urban II preaches about the oppression being inflicted on the Christians in the Middle East by the Muslim Seljuks. Christian churches are being destroyed and Christians attacked. The Pope calls for the Christians in the West to help.
{COUNCIL_OF_CLERMONT_TITLE}Council of Clermont
{COUNCIL_OF_TROYES_BODY}The Council of Troyes takes place. Its aim is to consider the claim of the Knights Templars represented by Hugues de Payen and Andre de Montbard and was brought about by Bernard of Clairvaux. The Council provides papal approval for the Templars and is resulting in many new recruits joining the order. The Order is provided it with its first rule, the Latin Rule. 
{COUNCIL_OF_TROYES_TITLE}Council of Troyes
{DANTE_BORN_BODY}Dante Alighieri is born in Florence. Later, he will write the Divine Comedy - perhaps the greatest literary expression of the Middle Ages - in Italian verse. Dante is extensively educated in literature, philosophy and Scholastic theology. His "Comedy" is saturated with the belief of earthly immortality through worthy deeds and the preparation of life everlasting.
{DANTE_BORN_TITLE}Dante Alighieri is born
{DENMARK_KING_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late Danish ruler, his heir has succeeded to the throne. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...	
{DENMARK_KING_EVENT_TITLE}The King of Denmark is dead!	
{DENMARK_REGENT_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late Danish ruler, a regent has been selected to administer the realm. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...	
{DENMARK_REGENT_EVENT_TITLE}End of a Dynasty?	
{DOMINICAN_ORDER_FOUNDED_BODY}The Dominican order is founded by St. Dominic of Spain and is authorized by Innocent III. Its purpose is to convert Muslims and Jews and to put an end to heresy. The Dominicans eventually become the main administrators of inquisitorial trials.
{DOMINICAN_ORDER_FOUNDED_TITLE}Dominican Order Founded
{DOOMSDAY_BOOK_BODY}The Doomsday Book which was commissioned by the late William the Conqueror of England in December 1085 has been completed. The first draft was completed in August 1086 and contained records for 13,418 settlements in the English counties south of the rivers Ribble and Tees (the border with Scotland at the time). An observer of the survey has noted that "there was no single hide nor a yard of land, nor indeed one ox nor one cow nor one pig which has been left out".
{DOOMSDAY_BOOK_TITLE}Doomsday Book Written
{EARTHQUAKE_IN_ALEPPO_BODY}The people of Aleppo have suffered terribly, as the very earth beneath the city and surrounding lands buckled and broke in what could only be described as a terrible act of divine wrath or punishment - tremors were felt all throughout. After such a cataclysmic event, Aleppo will take many years to recover fully.
{EARTHQUAKE_IN_ALEPPO_TITLE}Disaster Strikes Aleppo!
{EARTHQUAKE_IN_ALEXANDRIA_2_BODY}Those at Alexandria that lived to remember the last earthquake that ravaged the city have now had to endure this destructive nightmare twice! The people of this city can still take hope in the defiant survival of the Lighthouse, though its now huge wounds are a stark reminder of this place's misfortune.
{EARTHQUAKE_IN_ALEXANDRIA_2_TITLE}Alexandria Suffers Again!
{EARTHQUAKE_IN_ALEXANDRIA_BODY}An earthquake has shaken the entire eastern Mediterranean basin, most terribly so at the ancient city of Alexandria. Lives were lost in the ensuing chaos and destruction caused by falling buildings. Even the great Lighthouse that has stood for over a millennia bears scars from the tremendous power of the quake.
{EARTHQUAKE_IN_ALEXANDRIA_TITLE}Earthquake in Alexandria!
{EARTHQUAKE_IN_LISBON_BODY}An earthquake has shaken the earth under the city Lisbon, killing many and setting the city in flames. The losses were great, however life was slowly coming back to normal. No longer than a month after, a second earthquake struck Lisbon, making the people pay for their sins again... over 50,000 people died.
{EARTHQUAKE_IN_LISBON_TITLE}Earthquakes strike at Lisbon!
{EARTHQUAKE_IN_NAPLES_BODY}Sitting in the shadow of Vesuvius, the people of Naples have always known that they have lived with the constant threat of danger. However, the terrible earthquake that has recently brought down countless buildings and ended many lives is probably not the disaster they expected to befall them.
{EARTHQUAKE_IN_NAPLES_TITLE}Napoli Endures Earthquake!
{EARTHQUAKE_IN_CILICIA_BODY}	A mighty earthquake has struck in the region of Pamphylia with damage being felt within the Seljuk city of Iconium. Fortunately the centre of the destructive power wasn't so close to this major population centre, although the casualties in the region have still been significant.
{EARTHQUAKE_IN_CILICIA_TITLE}	Iconium Suffers Quake!
{EGYPT_KING_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late Fatimid ruler, his heir has succeeded to the throne. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...	
{EGYPT_KING_EVENT_TITLE}The Fatimid Caliph is dead!	
{EGYPT_REGENT_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late Fatimid ruler, a regent has been selected to administer the realm. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...	
{EGYPT_REGENT_EVENT_TITLE}End of a Dynasty?	
{ENGLAND_KING_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late English ruler, his heir has succeeded to the throne. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...	
{ENGLAND_KING_EVENT_TITLE}The King of England is dead!	
{ENGLAND_REGENT_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late English ruler, a regent has been selected to administer the realm. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...	
{ENGLAND_REGENT_EVENT_TITLE}End of a Dynasty?	
{FIRST_BLAST_FURNACE_BODY}A new way of working metal is now being practised in the village of Lapphyttan in Sweden, and adopted in western Europe. Housed in a great building, mighty water-driven bellows blast air into a furnace that produces a blaze so fierce and unworldly that the iron from within the ore flows out as a stream of molten metal!\n\nEven though the raw iron that pours from this new furnace is very brittle, vast amounts of the stuff can be made with relative ease, which a learned smith can then easily treat to produce incredibly resilient weapons and armour.
{FIRST_BLAST_FURNACE_TITLE}Man-made Inferno!
{FIRST_EUROPEAN_PAPER_BODY}Word is spreading across Europe on a new medium... Written on pressed paper! What has been an expensive luxury imported from the Middle East and beyond has now come to western Europe.\n\nA small mill devoted to pressing paper into sheets has been established in Xativa, south of Valencia. Although the ongoing Reconquista suggests that Islam is not welcome in Iberia, it is evident that some Muslim culture and innovations definitely are.
{FIRST_EUROPEAN_PAPER_TITLE}European Paper
{FIRST_EYEGLASSES_BODY}Reports are coming in from northern Italy of scholars placing delicate glass lenses in a thin metallic frame to be worn on the face. Apparently, if the lenses are made to the correct size they can help those with poor sight to see like normal, healthier citizens. Aesthetes among the scholarly community are concerned that wearing such a contraption will result in being teased or shunned.
{FIRST_EYEGLASSES_TITLE}Lucid Visions
{FIRST_INQUISITION_BODY}The Episcopal Inquisition, the first of the Inquisitions, has been established to deal with all of the heretics in Catholic Europe by a papal bull entitled "Ad abolendam", "For the purpose of doing away with". Its main target is the Cathars in southern France. However it is left to the local bishops to administer, who often do not live within their own dioceses, so proves quite ineffective.
{FIRST_INQUISITION_TITLE}The Episcopal Inquisition
{FIRST_MAGNETIC_COMPASS_BODY}It has been discovered that an ore from the Asia Minor region of Magnesia that attracts iron, also can make a piece of that metal orientate itself to point to the north - as reliably as a devout Muslim would turn to face Mecca.\n\nThis strange phenomena has been captured in a small device known as a 'compass' that cartographers and navigators have begun embracing in earnest, claiming it will take much of the guess work out of the art of exploration and map making.
{FIRST_MAGNETIC_COMPASS_TITLE}Scientific Breakthrough
{FIRST_MECHANICAL_CLOCK_BODY}An elaborate new time-measuring device has begun to appear in several places around Europe that does not rely upon water or the light of the sun to work. Scholars have explained that it has been discovered that the motion of a swinging object can be used to drive the 'clock' mechanism.\n\nThose that have seen one of these new mechanical clocks have suggested making one large enough to see from a distance would be useful.
{FIRST_MECHANICAL_CLOCK_TITLE}Time Machine Made
{FIRST_OIL_PAINTING_BODY}A Flemish painter, Jan van Eyck, is now championing an outlandish concept to produce paint created from seed oils rather than using tempera egg yolk. He claims that these 'oil paints' dry much more slowly, allowing the artist to take all the time needed to perfect each stroke and feature of their paintings.\n\nSome of the art establishment have declared that they are unconvinced as to the merits of oil paint, most likely because their specialised skills with tempera are about to become obsolete.
{FIRST_OIL_PAINTING_TITLE}Pioneer of Paint
{FIRST_PIANO_BODY}With the Papacy no longer denouncing polyphony, the musical technique where two melodies are united, we are now in an age where aspiring musical artists are pioneering new ways to make heavenly music.\n\nThe most recent advent in the musical world is an instrument known as a spinet. A true modern mechanical marvel, the spinet is driven by row of black and white keys, just like a pipe organ, that when pressed strike varying notes on strings cased within. The sounds it produces are not so powerful or profound as the pipe organ, making it something a wealthy noble or merchant could have in their home.
{FIRST_PIANO_TITLE}Portable Pipe Organ?
{FIRST_PRINTED_BIBLE_BODY}The same clergymen that were denouncing the printing press have now made a total about face, hailing Gutenberg as a spreader of the faith. The first book Gutenberg's printing company has been commissioned to publish is the Holy Bible itself.\n\nWhether this came about as a result of Gutenberg fearing retribution from the Papacy, or because the Catholic church is one of the few establishments wealthy enough to finance such a project matters little - Bibles will soon be readily accessible to the common man& Even if he lacks the skills needed to read it.
{FIRST_PRINTED_BIBLE_TITLE}Papacy Pro-Printing
{FIRST_PRINTING_PRESS_BODY}News has arrived from Mainz that a goldsmith named Johann Gutenberg has invented a machine capable of repeatedly printing an entire page of the written word. Called the 'printing press', this machine has rows of slots that hold raised letters on tiny metal blocks. So long as the letters are properly arranged into words and sentences, it is then a simple matter of pressing the metallic type onto ink, and then paper to do in moments what takes a scribe considerable time.\n\nThere are some members of the cloth already claiming that the mass-production of books may result in widespread literacy, which will in turn lead to the unsupervised consumption of heretical beliefs.
{FIRST_PRINTING_PRESS_TITLE}The Mechanical Scribe!
{FIRST_PUBLIC_CLOCK_BODY}The citizens of the city of Milan can now claim to be the most punctual in the known world, or at least, their overseers and taskmasters can claim to know when their workers are tardy. An expensive mechanical clock has been set atop a tower, so that everyone from prince to pauper may see the time displayed from the city streets.\n\nTypically, now that scholars and engineers have succeeded in creating a truly grand mechanical clock, the more malcontent members of the noble class have begun calling for a portable version of the device!
{FIRST_PUBLIC_CLOCK_TITLE}Time for Everyone
{FIRST_RUDDER_BODY}Arabic sailors have successfully adopted an old seafaring trick from the Far East, using a plate of wood called a 'rudder' at the rear of a ship to change its path through the water.\n\nSome outlandish notions are being raised by some of the more eccentric military strategists that suggest that wars will one day be waged at sea, and that the rudder is a vital step toward their vision being realised.
{FIRST_RUDDER_TITLE}Seafaring Innovation
{FIRST_SAWMILL_BODY}Great minds have found new ways to make light of some of the heaviest work. Sawing wood has always been slow work for even the strongest labourers, but cunning engineers have found a way to drive a great saw capable of planning an entire log by using water!\n\n
{FIRST_SAWMILL_TITLE}The Forest is Conquered!
{FIRST_WATCH_BODY}At last an inventor has found a means to create a portable timepiece! Peter Henlein, a locksmith from Nuremberg has created a small clock being dubbed the 'Nuremberg Egg' for its oval shape. Once its spring mechanism inside its shell is wound, the 'egg' will display the hour, for almost two full days.\n\nDespite still being large enough to leave an incredibly unseemly lump in one's pocket, being seen in possession of one of Henlein's Nuremberg Eggs has become 'the' trinket to be seen to possess - for the few that can afford one.
{FIRST_WATCH_TITLE}Portable Clock
{FIRST_WHEELBARROW_BODY}Tales of a clever invention from the Far East have recently inspired European peasants to come up with a simple labourer's aid they are referring to as the 'wheelbarrow' .\n\nBy placing a wheel at the front of a wooden stretcher, it has been discovered that a lone worker can move a heavy load of stone on their own, with little risk of injury. It could be as much of a boon for lords seeking to raise castles in quick time, as it will be for the serfs who shall have to build them.
{FIRST_WHEELBARROW_TITLE}A Boon for Builders
{FIRST_WINDMILL_BODY}Reports are coming in from across Western Europe of engineers who have created a miracle mill that requires no stream or river to power it. Supposedly, man has found a way to let the very winds themselves drive massive mill mechanisms, simply by catching it in sails on beams of wood. While the Windmill's effectiveness reportedly dies as the winds do, to those living far from running water, it is sure to be considered a Godsend.
{FIRST_WINDMILL_TITLE}Making the Wind Work
{FOOTBALL_BANNED_BODY}The Lord Mayor of London has issued a proclamation of the banning of some violent mob behaviour that the commoners seen enamoured with...\n\n"And whereas there is a great uproar in the City through certain tumults arising from the striking of great footballs in the field of the public - from which many evils perchance may arise - which may God forbid - we do command and do forbid, on the King's behalf, upon pain of imprisonment, that such games shall not be practised henceforth within this city."\n\nNow that this law has been passed, the establishment are confident that these 'football' events have no chance of becoming an obsession of religious proportions.
{FOOTBALL_BANNED_TITLE}Football Denounced
{FRANCE_KING_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late French ruler, his heir has succeeded to the throne. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...	
{FRANCE_KING_EVENT_TITLE}The King of France is dead!	
{FRANCE_REGENT_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late French ruler, a regent has been selected to administer the realm. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...	
{FRANCE_REGENT_EVENT_TITLE}End of a Dynasty?	
{FRANCIS_OF_ASSISI_BODY}Francis of Assisi (September 26, 1181 – October 3, 1226) dies. Son of a wealthy family, who started life as a mercenary solider, he became a Roman Catholic friar and the founded of the Order of Friars Minor “Order of Little Brothers”, more commonly known as the Franciscans in 1209. This order believes in a simple life of poverty as led by Christ, and observance of the Pope. In 1219 Francis left, together with a few companions, on a pilgrimage of non-violence to Egypt. Crossing the lines between the sultan and the Crusaders, he was received by the sultan Melek-el-Kamel who was so impressed with his devotion that on leaving he is quoted as saying “Pray for me that God may deign to reveal to me that law and faith which is most pleasing to him.”
{FRANCIS_OF_ASSISI_TITLE}Francis of Assisi Dies
{FRANCISCAN_ORDER_FOUNDED_BODY}The Franciscan order is founded by the famous Francis of Assisi and is authorized by Pope Innocent III. The pope himself probably sees in them a possible answer to his desire for an orthodox preaching force to counter heresy. Many legends cluster around the decisive audience of Francis with the Pope.
{FRANCISCAN_ORDER_FOUNDED_TITLE}Franciscan Order Founded
{GREAT_COMET_BODY}A great comet has been seen in the heavens, like a sabre it hangs there above us all. Calls have been made for the Pope to excommunicate this dark omen.
{GREAT_COMET_TITLE}Dark Omen
{GROTE_MANDENKE_BODY}An incredible south-westerly Atlantic gale like never seen before has struck the north-western tip of Europe, lashing England, right across to Denmark. Unstoppable storm tides have swept inland, killing many, and conditions at sea are dire enough to make sailing for the brave and foolish only.
{GROTE_MANDENKE_TITLE}The Great Drowning of Men
{GUNPOWDER_DISCOVERED_BODY}	In Europe, information of a terrible new compound called 'Gunpowder' are being told.  Information on it can be found in Roger Bacon's "De nullitate magiæ" at Oxford, published in 1216, or in his "Opus Maior" in 1248 where he describes a recipe for this new weapon:\n\n"We can, with saltpeter and other substances, compose artificially a fire that can be launched over long distances ... By only using a very small quantity of this material much light can be created accompanied by a horrible fracas. It is possible with it to destroy a town or an army ... In order to produce this artificial lightning and thunder it is necessary to take saltpeter, sulfur, and Luru Vopo Vir Can Utriet."\n\nOthers soon add to this, such as the Norwegian Konungs skuggsjá, where he mentions in its military chapter the use of "coal and sulphur" as the best weapon for ship-to-ship combat.\n\nHowever its not until the Moors use it for Cannons in there wars against the Spanish that its true power is seen.  It would be best to seek knowledge of this new technology quickly.
{GUNPOWDER_DISCOVERED_TITLE}A Deadly New Weapon!
{HANSEATIC_LEAGUE_BODY}The Hanseatic League is not so much a league of cities as it is a league of merchant associations within the cities of Northern Germany and the Baltic. Trading in these times is a dangerous and risky business and the only way for merchants to protect themselves is by travelling together. This banding together of merchants on the road led to their alliances at home as well. 
{HANSEATIC_LEAGUE_TITLE}Hanseatic League Founded
{HILDEGARD_OF_BINGEN_BODY}Renowned for her visions, treatises about theology, poetry, visions (Scivias), natural history and medicinal uses of plants, animals, trees and stones. She is the first composer whose biography is known. She founded a vibrant convent at Rupertsberg, where her musical plays are performed, and had advised bishops, popes, and kings.
{HILDEGARD_OF_BINGEN_TITLE}Hildegard of Bingen dies
{HRE_KING_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late German ruler, his heir has succeeded to the throne. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...	
{HRE_KING_EVENT_TITLE}The Holy Roman Emperor is dead!	
{HRE_REGENT_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late German ruler, a regent has been selected to administer the realm. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...	
{HRE_REGENT_EVENT_TITLE}End of a Dynasty?	
{HUNDRED_YEARS_WAR_BODY}Open hostilities broke out as French ships began ravaging coastal settlements on the English Channel. The French King Philip VI reclaimed the Gascon fief, citing feudal law and said that Edward has broken his oath (a felony) by not attending to the needs and demands of his lord. King Edward III responded by saying he is in fact the rightful heir to the French throne, and on All Saints' Day, Henry Burghersh, Bishop of Lincoln, arrived in Paris with the defiance of the king of England. War has been declared.
{HUNDRED_YEARS_WAR_TITLE}The beginning of the Hundred Years' War
{HUNGARY_KING_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late Hungarian ruler, his heir has succeeded to the throne. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...	
{HUNGARY_KING_EVENT_TITLE}The King of Hungary is dead!	
{HUNGARY_REGENT_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late Hungarian ruler, a regent has been selected to administer the realm. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...	
{HUNGARY_REGENT_EVENT_TITLE}End of a Dynasty?	
{INQUISITION_BODY}The papal inquisition is a respond to the failures of the Episcopal inquisition and is staffed by professionals, trained specifically for the job. Individuals are chosen from different orders and secular clergy, but primarily they come from the Dominican Order. The Dominicans are favoured for their history of anti-heresy, education, and skill in debate.
{INQUISITION_TITLE}The Papal Inquisition Begins
{JERUSALEM_CHRISTIAN_BODY}By the Grace of God, those who went forth in the name our Lord have captured Jerusalem. Thus the Holy city has been triumphantly reclaimed in the name of Christ. All of Christendom will rejoice, for God's Children may now find salvation in the Kingdom of Heaven.
{JERUSALEM_CHRISTIAN_TITLE}Jerusalem Captured	
{JERUSALEM_MUSLIM_BODY}Today the followers of the Prophet Mohammed rejoice. For Muslim armies have captured the Holy city of Jerusalem.
{JERUSALEM_MUSLIM_TITLE}Jerusalem Captured	
{JERUSALEM_PAGAN_BODY}This cannot be! The Holy city of Jerusalem has been disgraced by the pagan hordes, reminding the old history of Rome. It is everyones duty, to take up arms and free the Holy city from its suffering.
{JERUSALEM_PAGAN_TITLE}Jerusalem Captured	
{JERUSALEM_KING_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late ruler of Jerusalem, his heir has succeeded to the throne. The Order Brothers know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...	
{JERUSALEM_KING_EVENT_TITLE}The King of Jerusalem is dead!	
{JERUSALEM_REGENT_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late ruler of Jerusalem, a regent has been selected to administer the realm. The Order Brothers know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...	
{JERUSALEM_REGENT_EVENT_TITLE}End of a Dynasty?	
{KIEVAN_RUS_KING_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late Kievan Rus ruler, his heir has succeeded to the throne. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...	
{KIEVAN_RUS_KING_EVENT_TITLE}The Kievan Veliky Knyaz is dead!	
{KIEVAN_RUS_REGENT_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late Kievan Rus ruler, a regent has been selected to administer the realm. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...	
{KIEVAN_RUS_REGENT_EVENT_TITLE}End of a Dynasty?	
{KWAREZM_KING_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late Khwarezmian ruler, his heir has succeeded to the throne. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...	
{KWAREZM_KING_EVENT_TITLE}The Khwarezmian Shah is dead!	
{KWAREZM_REGENT_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late Khwarezmian ruler, a regent has been selected to administer the realm. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...	
{KWAREZM_REGENT_EVENT_TITLE}End of a Dynasty?	
{LATERAN_COUNCIL1_BODY}A great meeting of all of the Bishops and Archbishops of the West has ended. The meeting has introduced many new canon laws. These laws include provisions forbidding those of the church from marrying or taking concubines, separation of spiritual and temporal affairs, and provides for safeguards for the families of crusaders. Also excommunication is now the punishment for any layman appropriating church offerings or fortifying a church as a stronghold.
{LATERAN_COUNCIL1_TITLE}The First Lateran Council
{LATERAN_COUNCIL2_BODY}The Church has finished another great meeting, rectifying some of the issues that have appeared due to the schism within the church and the appearance of an antipope; Anacletus II. New canon laws have been created, one of which will be of interest to the knights of Europe, that of forbidding, on the pain of deprivation of a Catholic burial, tournaments and jousts that endanger life.
{LATERAN_COUNCIL2_TITLE}The Second Lateran Council
{LATERAN_COUNCIL3_BODY}Another meeting of the Catholic Church has occurred which condemns the Waldensian and Cathar heresies, as well as enacting new canon law. One law decrees that only the cardinals shall have the privilege of electing the Pope. It also forbids tournaments, organizes asylums for lepers, and calls on the princes to suppress heresy, requires every cathedral church to appoint a master to teach the clerics and the poor scholars of the church (this action helps launch cathedral schools that later became universities). Finally, the council calls for a prohibition on Christians supplying Saracens with ship building materials.
{LATERAN_COUNCIL3_TITLE}The Third Lateran Council
{LATERAN_COUNCIL4_BODY}In what is becoming known as the “Great Council”, this November in the year of our Lord seventy-one patriarchs and metropolitans, including the Patriarchs of Constantinople and of Jerusalem, four hundred and twelve bishops, and nine hundred abbots and priors have met. The Patriarchs of Antioch and Alexandria were represented by delegates. Envoys appeared from the Holy Roman Emperor, from the Latin Emperor of Constantinople, from the Kings of France, England, Aragon, Hungary, Cyprus, and Jerusalem, and from other princes. It defines the central dogmas of Roman Christianity, acknowledges the sacraments of the Eucharist and penance needed for salvation. The council also asserts that the Pope's power over the Church and over the kings of Europe. In preparation for a forthcoming Crusade it imposes a four years' peace on all Christian peoples and princes, and enjoins the bishops to reconcile all enemies.
{LATERAN_COUNCIL4_TITLE}The Fourth Lateran Council
{MAGNA_CARTA_BODY}Magna Carta was written because of disagreements between Pope Innocent III, King John and his English barons about the rights of the King. Magna Carta required the king to renounce certain rights, respect certain legal procedures and accept that the will of the king could be bound by the law. It explicitly protected certain rights of the King's subjects - whether free or unfree - most notably the right of Habeas Corpus.
{MAGNA_CARTA_TITLE}Magna Carta Signed
{MALLEUS_MALEFICARUM_BODY}In these dark times that see the Lord's children under constant exposure to heresy, and in extreme cases, witchcraft, at last we have been armed with the knowledge to drive back and defeat the forces of darkness - the Malleus Maleficarum, meaning, "The Hammer of Witches".\n\nThis tome has immediately been accepted as the definitive instruction set for a trial of heresy, covering everything from detecting witchcraft through to how to forcibly purge a human vessel of sin.
{MALLEUS_MALEFICARUM_TITLE}The Hammer of Witches'
{MATTHEW_EDESSA_BODY}Matthew of Edessa, the great Armenian patriot, superior abbot and historian dies at the siege of Edessa. He was a long time opponent of both the Latin and Greek churches.
{MATTHEW_EDESSA_TITLE}Matthew of Edessa dies
{MEDICI_FAMILY_BODY}The Medici banking family dominates the government of Florence.
{MEDICI_FAMILY_TITLE}Medici Banking Family
{MILAN_KING_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late Genoese ruler, his heir has succeeded to the throne. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...	
{MILAN_KING_EVENT_TITLE}The Doge of Genoa is dead!	
{MILAN_REGENT_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late Genoese ruler, a regent has been selected to administer the realm. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...	
{MILAN_REGENT_EVENT_TITLE}End of a Dynasty?
{MONGOLS_KING_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late Mongolian ruler, his heir has succeeded to the throne. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...	
{MONGOLS_KING_EVENT_TITLE}The Mongolian Khan is dead!	
{MONGOLS_REGENT_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late Mongolian ruler, a regent has been selected to administer the realm. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...	
{MONGOLS_REGENT_EVENT_TITLE}End of a Dynasty?		
{MONGOLS_INVASION_WARN_BODY}News has spread from merchants of the far east, who speak in great fear of a fierce warlord from Mongolia named Genghis Khan, who has amassed an unstoppable horde of cavalry. These Mongols are reportedly sweeping across Transoxania at a frightening rate, and look set on continuing westward, either north or south of the Caspian sea.
{MONGOLS_INVASION_WARN_TITLE}A New Threat!
{MONGOLS_INVASION_WARN_MONGOLS_BODY}The so-called Khwazermid Empire, which killed our envoys two years ago will now pay for their treachery. Our army is unstoppable, and so we shall crush their puny kingdom.\nEvery castle will fall, every city will burn!\n\nWe have already seized control of Urgench, showing the might of our army!
{MONGOLS_INVASION_WARN_MONGOLS_TITLE}Time to Take Vengeance!
{MONGOLS_INVASION_WARN_KWAREZM_BODY}The Mongolian envoys which we killed not longer than 2 years ago did speak the truth! The Horde is now trying to take vengeance for the death of their diplomats, sending the might of their cavalry against us. They will regret the day they set foot in our glorious Empire.
{MONGOLS_INVASION_WARN_KWAREZM_TITLE}The Horde Attacks!
{MOORS_KING_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late Moorish ruler, his heir has succeeded to the throne. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...	
{MOORS_KING_EVENT_TITLE}The Almoravid Emir is dead!	
{MOORS_REGENT_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late Moorish ruler, a regent has been selected to administer the realm. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...	
{MOORS_REGENT_EVENT_TITLE}End of a Dynasty?	
{NETHERLANDS_FLOOD_BODY}Dykes have broken across the lowlands. Estimates say that 100,000 people have died.
{NETHERLANDS_FLOOD_TITLE}Dykes Break
{NEW_ERA_BEGINS_BODY}The early Middle Ages have ended. The beginning of the Late Middle Ages witnesses the invention of new weapons and armour, greatly aiding overseas expansion and enhancing trade between places such as Italy and the North. Boniface VIII calls the first papal "jubilee," thereby recognizing pilgrimages to Rome instead of Jerusalem, which is no longer accessible to the West.\n\n(New Mercenaries available) 
{NEW_ERA_BEGINS_TITLE}A New Era Begins
{NORWAY_KING_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late Norwegian ruler, his heir has succeeded to the throne. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...	
{NORWAY_KING_EVENT_TITLE}The King of Norway is dead!	
{NORWAY_REGENT_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late Norwegian ruler, a regent has been selected to administer the realm. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...	
{NORWAY_REGENT_EVENT_TITLE}End of a Dynasty?	
{NOTRE_DAME_BODY}Bishop Maurice de Sully deems the current Parisian cathedral unworthy of its lofty role, and has had it demolished shortly after he assumed the title of Bishop of Paris. Construction has begun in 1163, in the reign of Louis VII, construction of the west front, with its distinctive two towers, will begin circa 1200, before the nave had been completed, contrary to normal construction practice. Over the construction period, numerous architects will work on the site, which will lead to differing styles at different heights of the west front and towers. In the futures a rose window and great halls beneath the towers is envisaged. The building is not expected to be fully completed until 1345.
{NOTRE_DAME_TITLE}Notre Dame de Paris founded
{OMAR_KHAYYAM_BODY}Ghiyas od-Din Abul-Fatah Omar ibn Ibrahim Khayyam Nishaburi or Omar Khayyam the great Persian poet, mathematician, philosopher and astronomer who lived in Persia has died. While best known for his poetry and quatrains (rubaiyaas) in Rubaiyat of Omar Khayyam, he made substantial mathematical contributions, including his Treatise on Demonstration of Problems of Algebra, which gives a geometric method for solving cubic equations by intersecting a hyperbola with a circle. He also contributed to calendar reform and may have proposed a heliocentric theory well before Copernicus. The calendar he created is known as Jalali calendar, after the Sultan, and is in force across Greater Iran for the foreseeable future, being more accurate than the Gregorian calendar. 
{OMAR_KHAYYAM_TITLE}Omar Khayyam dies
{OMNE_DATUM_OPTIMUM_BODY}Omne Datum Optimum (All good things), the first Papal Bull granting privileges to the Templars, is issued by the pope. Milites Templi (Soldiers of the Temple) and Militia Dei (Soldiers of God) follow in 1144 and 1145.
{OMNE_DATUM_OPTIMUM_TITLE}Omne Datum Optimum
{PALMYRA_DESTROYED_BODY}Grave tidings, the once great city of Palmyra has been destroyed by a massive earthquake. For over a millennia this city has been a stop along the caravan routes from China and has enjoyed great wealth. Now it is only ruins.
{PALMYRA_DESTROYED_TITLE}Palmyra Destroyed by Earthquake
{PLAYER_FIRST_GREAT_JAMA_BODY}The Muslims do not worship symbols, for the prophet, blessed be his name, had decreed that to represent the divine with an icon or image is blasphemy in the extreme. However, nobody could really deny that the sight of this grand mosque serves as a shining example of the might and wisdom of Islam.	
{PLAYER_FIRST_GREAT_JAMA_TITLE}First Great Jama	
{PLAYER_FIRST_HUGE_CATHEDRAL_BODY}If there were any lingering doubts as to the power of the church, they were dispelled once the people gazed upon God’s greatest house on earth. Its towering presence here shall ensure Christian dominance throughout the land.
{PLAYER_FIRST_HUGE_CATHEDRAL_TITLE}Worlds First Huge Cathedral
{POLAND_KING_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late Polish ruler, his heir has succeeded to the throne. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...	
{POLAND_KING_EVENT_TITLE}The Polish Senior Duke is dead!	
{POLAND_REGENT_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late Polish ruler, a regent has been selected to administer the realm. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...	
{POLAND_REGENT_EVENT_TITLE}End of a Dynasty?	
{PORTUGAL_KING_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late Portuguese ruler, his heir has succeeded to the throne. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...	
{PORTUGAL_KING_EVENT_TITLE}The King of Portugal is dead!	
{PORTUGAL_REGENT_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late Portuguese ruler, a regent has been selected to administer the realm. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...	
{PORTUGAL_REGENT_EVENT_TITLE}End of a Dynasty?	
{RELIGIONS_SECTS_BOOK_BODY}Muhammad al-Shahrastani (1086-1153), the great Muslim scholar, philosopher and theologian, has completed his great work, Kitab al–Milal wa al-Nihal or 'The Book of Sects and Creeds'. This book studies the histories and teachings of the religions of the world. The book is remarkably unbiased and impartial, much more so than anything so far written within Europe. 
{RELIGIONS_SECTS_BOOK_TITLE}A Treatise on Religion
{RUMI_BODY}Mawlana Jalal-ad-Din Muhammad Rumi (September 30, 1207–December 17, 1273), arguably the greatest Persian Sufi poet, jurist and theologian dies. Living most of his life in the Seljuk Empire, his many books, poetry and songs inspire all who read them. Chief amongst these is Masnavi-ye Manavi (Spiritual Couplets), a six-volume poem regarded by many Sufis as second in importance only to the Qur'an itself. After his death, his followers form the Mevlevi Order, better known as the Whirling Dervishes, who believe in performing their worship in the form of a dance and music ceremony called the sema.
{RUMI_TITLE}Rumi dies
{RUSSIA_KING_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late Novgorodian ruler, his heir has succeeded to the throne. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...	
{RUSSIA_KING_EVENT_TITLE}The Novgorodian Knyaz is dead!	
{RUSSIA_REGENT_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late Novgorodian ruler, a regent has been selected to administer the realm. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...	
{RUSSIA_REGENT_EVENT_TITLE}End of a Dynasty?	
{SALADIN_DIES_BODY}Islam’s most chivalrous knight, the great sultan of Egypt, Saladin, has died. Founder of the Ayyubid dynasty he restored Sunnism in Egypt, who consider him a Waliullah, a person religiously close to God. When his treasury was opened there was not enough money in it to pay for his funeral; for he had given most of his money away in charity. A tomb will be made for him in Damascus.
{SALADIN_DIES_TITLE}Saladin dies
{SAMARKAND_SACKED_BODY}Grave tidings from the East. The great Persian city of Samarkand has been sacked. The ancient city has been ravaged by hordes from the East and very few have survived to tell the tale. God willing this horde will turn back home, but you should prepare for the worst should they not.
{SAMARKAND_SACKED_TITLE}Samarkand Sacked!
{SCIENCE_ALCHEMY_BOOK_BODY}Robert of Chester, an English translator has completed his transcription of the Liber de Compositione Alchemiae, or more simply, the Book of the Composition of Alchemy. Originally an Arabic text, this grand compendium of scientific and alchemical discoveries and musings is being deemed an affront to holy mandate by the establishment... But rumour has it most scholars would risk being associated with heretical beliefs to glean the knowledge hidden within its pages.
{SCIENCE_ALCHEMY_BOOK_TITLE}Liber de Compositione Alchemiae
{SCIENCE_DA_VINCI_ORNITHOPTER_BODY}Leonardo da Vinci, an Italian mastermind known for his revolutionary artistic works and ingenious inventions has concocted his most ambitious and eldritch design yet. His fascination with the science of flight has culminated in his 'Ornithopter' design.\n\nLooking something akin to a windmill sail atop a horseless carriage, many other scholars are laughing, suggesting da Vinci should go back to his concepts based upon attaching wings to the human body.
{SCIENCE_DA_VINCI_ORNITHOPTER_TITLE}Machines that Fly?
{SCIENCE_DE_DOCTA_IGNORANTIA_BODY}A Catholic scholar, Nicholas of Cusa has published a series of scientific and philosophical claims, bundled together under the somewhat arrogant title of De Docta Ignorantia - literally meaning, 'Of Learned Ignorance' .\n\nHis theories include the notion that the Earth is not the centre of the Universe, and that it actually orbits the Sun. Even more fantastical, he even attests that the stars of the night sky are actually distant suns themselves!
{SCIENCE_DE_DOCTA_IGNORANTIA_TITLE}Of Learned Ignorance
{SCIENCE_MATHS_ZERO_EUROPE_BODY}A mathematician from Pisa by the name of Fibonacci has published a new work entitled 'Liber Abaci'. He has adopted some Hindu-Arabic theories involving a number that has no value, claiming this is a vital step for making calculations on a grand scale.\n\nDespite managing to excite western scholars, the Liber Abaci's revelations offer few insights to the common man... who typically spends all his life dealing with things of 'no value'.
{SCIENCE_MATHS_ZERO_EUROPE_TITLE}The Hero of Zero
{SCIENCE_WEATHER_FORECAST_BODY}An aspiring English scholar by the name of Walter Merle claims that he is able to predict the weather - unlike the mystical ramblings of yesteryear's heretical pagans who claimed to have a spiritual insight into when the heavens will open up, Merle has stated he can do this simply by scientific observation.\n\nApparently Merle's predictions are correct more often than not, but his system is still being perfected. Surely it will only be a matter of months now before man knows exactly how the weather will behave.
{SCIENCE_WEATHER_FORECAST_TITLE}Bold Predictions
{SCOTLAND_KING_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late Scottish ruler, his heir has succeeded to the throne. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...	
{SCOTLAND_KING_EVENT_TITLE}The King of Scotland is dead!	
{SCOTLAND_REGENT_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late Scottish ruler, a regent has been selected to administer the realm. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...	
{SCOTLAND_REGENT_EVENT_TITLE}End of a Dynasty?	
{SCOTLAND_WALLACE_BODY}The Fires of Independence burn brightly in Scotland. Weary of aggression from Scotland's neighbours, a new hero has emerged to unite Scotland's clans. His name is William Wallace. A minor noble he may be, but behind him marches thousands of warriors. Each one with freedom in his heart and a sword in his hand	
{SCOTLAND_WALLACE_TITLE}William Wallace Emerges! 	
{SHOTA_RUSTAVELI_BODY}Shota Rustaveli (c.1172 - c.1216), the Georgian poet, considered to be one of the greatest representatives of the literature of the Eastern European medieval world has died. He is best known for Vepkhistqaosani "The Knight in the Panther's Skin", an epic adventure about friendship and courtly love.
{SHOTA_RUSTAVELI_TITLE}Shota Rustaveli dies
{SICILY_KING_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late Sicilian ruler, his heir has succeeded to the throne. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...	
{SICILY_KING_EVENT_TITLE}The King of Sicily is dead!	
{SICILY_REGENT_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late Sicilian ruler, a regent has been selected to administer the realm. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...	
{SICILY_REGENT_EVENT_TITLE}End of a Dynasty?	
{SPAIN_KING_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late Castilian ruler, his heir has succeeded to the throne. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...	
{SPAIN_KING_EVENT_TITLE}The King of Castile and León is dead!	
{SPAIN_REGENT_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late Castilian ruler, a regent has been selected to administer the realm. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...	
{SPAIN_REGENT_EVENT_TITLE}End of a Dynasty?	
{SPANISH_INQUISITION_BODY}The Inquisition starts in Spain and ultimately surpasses the earlier medieval Inquisition, in both scope and intensity. Conversos and New Christians are targeted because of their close relations to the Jewish community, many of whom are Jews in all but their name. Fear of Jewish influence led Queen Isabella and King Ferdinand to write a petition to the Pope asking permission to start an Inquisition in Spain. Tomas de Torquemada is the inquisitor-general for most of Spain, he sets tribunals in many cities. Also heading the Inquisition in Spain are two Dominican monks, Miguel de Morillo and Juan de San Martin.
{SPANISH_INQUISITION_TITLE}The Spanish Inquisition begins
{SUMMA_THEOLOGICA_BODY}Thomas Aquinas' work, the Summa Theologiae is published. It is intended as a manual for beginners as a compilation of all of the main theological teachings of this time. It is not designed or ordered as an apologetic work directed toward non-Catholics, but it does contain a summary of the reasoning’s for almost all points of the Catholic faith.
{SUMMA_THEOLOGICA_TITLE}Summa Theologiae Published
{TEUTONIC_ORDER_BODY}After the loss of Jerusalem in 1187, some merchants from Lubeck and Bremen took up the idea and founded a field hospital for the duration of the siege of Acre, which became the nucleus of the Teutonic Order. Celestine III recognized it by granting the friars Augustinian Rule. Based on the model of the Knights Templar it is, however, transformed into a military order and the head of the order becomes known as the Grand Master (Magister Hospitalis). It receives Papal orders for crusades to take and hold Jerusalem for Latin Christianity and defend the Holy Land against the Muslim Saracens.\n\nHowever, it is the pagans of Lithuania, that will feel the full force of the Order’s zeal and the sting of their swords first.
{TEUTONIC_ORDER_TITLE}Teutonic Order Founded
{TEUTONIC_ORDER_INVASION_BODY}With the permission of Duke Conrad of Masovia, the Masovian nobility and the pope himself, the Teutonic Order, lead by their Grandmaster Hermann von Salza, begins their lengthy campaign to Christianize pagan Prussia.
{TEUTONIC_ORDER_INVASION_TITLE}The Teutonic Order Emerges!
{TEUTONIC_ORDER_KING_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the Teutonic Order's Hochmeister, a successor has been elected to carry the title. The Order Brothers know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...	
{TEUTONIC_ORDER_KING_EVENT_TITLE}The Teutonic Grandmaster is dead!	
{TEUTONIC_ORDER_REGENT_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the Teutonic Order's Hochmeister, a successor has been elected to carry the title. The Order Brothers know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...
{TEUTONIC_ORDER_REGENT_EVENT_TITLE}The Teutonic Grandmaster is dead!	
{THE_BOOK_OF_SENTENCES_BODY}A student of Peter Abelard, Peter Lombard, writes the Book of Sentences which answers fundamental questions of theology with passages from the Bible and various Christian thinkers. His book becomes a standard text in all universities by the thirteenth century.
{THE_BOOK_OF_SENTENCES_TITLE}The Book of Sentences
{THE_GIRALDA_BODY}The rulers of Seville have completed a masterpiece of architecture – an enormously tall Minaret which is rumoured to be the tallest building on earth. The building is a composite of numerous cultures, including some Roman ruins. The tower is served by many ramps, which are wide enough for the muezzin to ride his horse to the top of when going to call the Adhan. It is an outstanding example of the Gothic and Baroque architectural styles.
{THE_GIRALDA_TITLE}A Magnificent Minaret
{THE_MONGOLS_EMERGE_BODY}It is easy to become comfortable with the enemy you know, our familiar foes. But to discount the menaces that lurk beyond the known world is to risk a rude awakening that can become a nightmare. This nightmare is the Mongol invasion.
{THE_MONGOLS_EMERGE_TITLE}The Mongols Invade!
{THE_MONGOLS_EMERGE_KWAREZM_BODY}	Oh mighty Sultan, the Mongols led by their great lord Genghis Khan has arrived on out lands.  It seems he feels insulted by our actions and is intent on destroying us.
{THE_MONGOLS_EMERGE_KWAREZM_TITLE}	The Mongols Invade!
{MONGOLS_BLUE_HORDE_CAUCASUS_BODY}	A body of Mongol forces has thrust into the Caucasus, posing a threat to all states in the area.\n\nIn 1220, under orders from Genghis Khan, Subutai led a fierce, battle-hardened Mongol horde out of the steppes into the Caucasus on a reconnaissance mission. In that same year, they defeated a Georgian-Armenian army, many times the size of their own, at the Battle of Khunan. Subutai continued to plunder Georgian territory until, in 1221, his army was repulsed by another force of Georgians. The Mongols withdrew to the Caspian Sea and proceeded to march North into Cuman territory, where they now stand, ready to raid and destroy Cuman and Georgian lands alike. This is undoubtedly the toughest challenge any of the Russian or Caucasian states have faced. Can they withstand these fierce steppe warriors and maintain their freedom?\n\nHistorically, Subutai and the Mongols defeated a coalition of Rus/Kipchak forces in the Battle at the Khalka River, before returning to Genghis Khan and the main Mongol force in Asia. 
{MONGOLS_BLUE_HORDE_CAUCASUS_TITLE}	The Blue Horde Arrives in the Caucasus
{MONGOLS_BLUE_HORDE_KIEV_BODY}	A vast horde of battle-hungry Mongols has stormed into Kievan territories, slaughtering any who resist them.\n\n14 years after the initial raid on the Caucasus, the Mongols have returned in greater numbers with the single aim of destroying the Principality of Kievan Rus. Having annihilated the Volga Bulgarians and the Kypchaks, Batu Khan (leader of the invasion) leads his vast horde of fierce Mongol riders to the gates of Kiev. The horde seems unstoppable but were an alliance of Russian states to occur, they might halt the unforgiving advance of Batu and his army.\n\nHistorically, Batu and the Mongols mercilessly swept through Russia, sacking fifteen major cities and defeating any Kievan forces sent against them until, in 1240, after a long siege they finally sacked the capital, Kiev.
{MONGOLS_BLUE_HORDE_KIEV_TITLE}	The Blue Horde Returns
{MONGOLS_BLUE_HORDE_HUNGARY_BODY}	The Mongol Blue Horde continues to ravage across the land, now striking into Eastern Europe and threatening the kingdoms of Poland, Hungary and the Balkans.\n\nAfter the destruction of the Principality of Kiev in 1237/38, Batu Khan began the planning of the largest invasion yet. It’s target: Eastern Europe. The invasion began in 1241 and consists of two main forces – one striking into Poland and the other into Hungary.\n\nHistorically, the Mongol army in Poland annihilated Polish resistance in the Battle of Legnica and continued to pillage Silesia and other Polish territories, before combinging with the main Mongol forces in Hungary. This combined Mongol army inflicted a decisive defeat on the Hungarian King at the Battle of Mohi, before the Eastern Europe advance was halted due to the recalling of the major commanders (including Batu Khan) to Mongolia.
{MONGOLS_BLUE_HORDE_HUNGARY_TITLE}	The Blue Horde reaches Europe
{MONGOLS_HORDE_BAGHDAD_BODY}	A huge Mongol Horde has set forth under the leadership of Hulagu Khan to attack the great city of Baghdad. In this they are aided by Christians as well, seeking to weaken the Muslim Infidels who occupy Bagdhad. These include Franks from Antioch, Georgians and a large force of Armenian infantry. The horde is the largest ever fielded by the Mongols and is a force to be feared by all, no matter how distant the threat might seem. Should the city fall, many fear for the works within its Great Library and the ancient architecture present within its walls.\n\nHistorically, the Mongols attacked with great ferocity and the city capitulated after a short and painless siege for the Mongols. Once inside the city, an orgy of bloodletting ensued, conducted with great efficiency by Hulagu Khan. It is estimated that hundreds of thousands of citizens were massacred within a single week and the Caliph and his family were publicly executed. 
{MONGOLS_HORDE_BAGHDAD_TITLE}	The Golden Horde reaches Baghdad
{THOMAS_BECKET_BODY}Thomas Becket (c.1118 – December 29, 1170), once Chancellor of England and Archbishop of Canterbury, who has long been in contention with the king of England has been murder in Canterbury Cathedral. During Vespers, four wicked knights entered and slew him most vilely. The faithful across Europe have already declared him a martyr! The king at some point will have to perform a public penance at the tomb, which is fast becoming one of the great pilgrimage sites of England.
{THOMAS_BECKET_TITLE}Thomas Becket Murdered
{TIMURIDS_KING_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late Timurid ruler, his heir has succeeded to the throne. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...	
{TIMURIDS_KING_EVENT_TITLE}The Emir of the Timurids is dead!	
{TIMURIDS_REGENT_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late Timurid ruler, a regent has been selected to administer the realm. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...	
{TIMURIDS_REGENT_EVENT_TITLE}End of a Dynasty?		
{THE_TIMURIDS_EMERGE_BODY}After facing the terror of the Mongol invasion, nobody would have dreamed that a serious peril could ever rise from the east again. However, Timur the Lame, a mighty warlord from Transoxania, has arrived on the eastern borders of our maps, bringing with him a legacy of conquest that cannot be ignored.\nHaving already conquered Persia, and distant India, Timur is certain to bring with him something exotic to show the people of the west. Something they will be sure to remember... as long as they live.\nThe mighty war machine of Timur the Lame has stormed into the lands surrounding %S.
{THE_TIMURIDS_EMERGE_TITLE}The Timurids Invade!
{TIMURIDS_INVASION_WARN_BODY}The Mongol invasion was a terror that the rulers of the western world were simply not ready to face, but if the stories of travellers are to be paid any heed then there is an even greater threat on its way!
{TIMURIDS_INVASION_WARN_TITLE}An Even Greater Threat?
{TORRE_DEL_ORO_BODY}A magnificent addition to the fortifications of Sevilla, the 'Tower of the Gold' has been started by the Almohades. This twelve-sided watchtower protects access to Sevilla from the Guadalquivir River by employing a chain to block the river. Its name comes from the plans to cover its dome in golden tiles. 
{TORRE_DEL_ORO_TITLE}A Grand Tower in Sevilla
{TURKS_KING_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late Seljuk ruler, his heir has succeeded to the throne. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...	
{TURKS_KING_EVENT_TITLE}The Seljuk Sultan is dead!	
{TURKS_REGENT_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late Seljuk ruler, a regent has been selected to administer the realm. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...	
{TURKS_REGENT_EVENT_TITLE}End of a Dynasty?	
{VENICE_KING_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late Venetian ruler, his heir has succeeded to the throne. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...	
{VENICE_KING_EVENT_TITLE}The Venetian Doge is dead!	
{VENICE_REGENT_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late Venetian ruler, a regent has been selected to administer the realm. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...	
{VENICE_REGENT_EVENT_TITLE}End of a Dynasty?	
{WORLD_IS_ROUND_BODY}Over the centuries several scholars have suggested that the world could be round, but most of them were burned at the stake as heretics, so the theory hasn't been particularly popular. However, with new advances in the fields of Astronomy, enough of the learned men of the world have accepted that the theory is well worth testing... Perhaps if someone were to establish a trade route to the far east by sailing west, they would both bring the debate to a close, as well as establish a trade lane that is most lucrative.
{WORLD_IS_ROUND_TITLE}The World is Round
{WORMS_CONCORDAT_BODY}The Concordat of Worms, or sometimes called the Pactum Calixtinum, is an agreement between Pope Calixtus II and Holy Roman Emperor Henry V near the city of Worms. It brings to an end the first phase of the power struggle between the Papacy and the Holy Roman Emperors. The King was recognized as having the right to invest bishops with secular authority ("by the lance") in the territories they governed, but not with sacred authority.
{WORMS_CONCORDAT_TITLE}Concordat of Worms
{YUNUS_EMRE_BODY}Yunus Emre (c1238–c1320) the greatly loved Turkish poet and Sufi mystic has died. His poems, written in the tradition of Anatolian folk poetry, mainly concern divine love and human destiny and are composed in the spoken Turkish language (rather than Persian or Arabic) of the area,. He is known to have occasionally used tekerlemeler (riddles) as a poetic device.
{YUNUS_EMRE_TITLE}Yunus Emre dies
{DIFFICULTY_EASY_BODY}                        Campaign Difficulty: Easy\n\nThanks for downloading and playing Stainless Steel!\nInformation about the mod can be obtained easily at www.twcenter.net, at the Stainless Steel sub forums. Game play hints or tricks, available submods, support, suggestions thread or epic after-action reports are all awaiting there. Be sure to visit us and say hi if you haven't done so yet! Feedback is always warmly welcomed.\n\n                     The Stainless Steel 6.4 team:\n      gracul, King Kong, Point Blank, Byg, Caesar Clivus\n       Rozanov, Germanicu5, y2day, Awellesley, Meneth\n                         cedric37, bane_tw, Ishan\n\n                                 Beta testers:\n          Smikis, Pedrol, sancco, TheColdTruth, Zanze\n       CamilleBonparte, adecoy95, nonnob3, Navajo Joe\n\n               Big thanks to everyone at the forums!\n                                   Have fun!
{DIFFICULTY_EASY_TITLE}From the team...
{DIFFICULTY_MEDIUM_BODY}                      Campaign Difficulty: Medium\n\nThanks for downloading and playing Stainless Steel!\nInformation about the mod can be obtained easily at www.twcenter.net, at the Stainless Steel sub forums. Game play hints or tricks, available submods, support, suggestions thread or epic after-action reports are all awaiting there. Be sure to visit us and say hi if you haven't done so yet! Feedback is always warmly welcomed.\n\n                     The Stainless Steel 6.4 team:\n      gracul, King Kong, Point Blank, Byg, Caesar Clivus\n       Rozanov, Germanicu5, y2day, Awellesley, Meneth\n                         cedric37, bane_tw, Ishan\n\n                                 Beta testers:\n          Smikis, Pedrol, sancco, TheColdTruth, Zanze\n       CamilleBonparte, adecoy95, nonnob3, Navajo Joe\n\n               Big thanks to everyone at the forums!\n                                   Have fun!
{DIFFICULTY_MEDIUM_TITLE}From the team...
{DIFFICULTY_HARD_BODY}                        Campaign Difficulty: Hard\n\nThanks for downloading and playing Stainless Steel!\nInformation about the mod can be obtained easily at www.twcenter.net, at the Stainless Steel sub forums. Game play hints or tricks, available submods, support, suggestions thread or epic after-action reports are all awaiting there. Be sure to visit us and say hi if you haven't done so yet! Feedback is always warmly welcomed.\n\n                     The Stainless Steel 6.4 team:\n      gracul, King Kong, Point Blank, Byg, Caesar Clivus\n       Rozanov, Germanicu5, y2day, Awellesley, Meneth\n                         cedric37, bane_tw, Ishan\n\n                                 Beta testers:\n          Smikis, Pedrol, sancco, TheColdTruth, Zanze\n       CamilleBonparte, adecoy95, nonnob3, Navajo Joe\n\n               Big thanks to everyone at the forums!\n                                   Have fun!
{DIFFICULTY_HARD_TITLE}From the team...
{DIFFICULTY_VERY_HARD_BODY}                    Campaign Difficulty: Very Hard\n\nThanks for downloading and playing Stainless Steel!\nInformation about the mod can be obtained easily at www.twcenter.net, at the Stainless Steel sub forums. Game play hints or tricks, available submods, support, suggestions thread or epic after-action reports are all awaiting there. Be sure to visit us and say hi if you haven't done so yet! Feedback is always warmly welcomed.\n\n                     The Stainless Steel 6.4 team:\n      gracul, King Kong, Point Blank, Byg, Caesar Clivus\n       Rozanov, Germanicu5, y2day, Awellesley, Meneth\n                         cedric37, bane_tw, Ishan\n\n                                 Beta testers:\n          Smikis, Pedrol, sancco, TheColdTruth, Zanze\n       CamilleBonparte, adecoy95, nonnob3, Navajo Joe\n\n               Big thanks to everyone at the forums!\n                                   Have fun!
{DIFFICULTY_VERY_HARD_TITLE}From the team...
{GREAT_FAIR_BODY}	Sire, a great trade fair could be held at your capital, do you wish to fund this?\n\nIt will cost 2500 Florins, but may give your Merchants and Governors a greater knowledge of trading. Of course declining may upset your merchants.
{GREAT_FAIR_TITLE}	Great Trade Fair
{GREAT_TOURNEY_BODY}	Sire, A great tournament could be held at your capital, do you wish to fund this?\n\nIt will cost 3000 Florins, but may give your knights the fighting edge they need and allow the people to view the royal princesses. Of course declining to fund such may be seen as a lack of confidence in their prowess.
{GREAT_TOURNEY_TITLE}	Great Tournament
{GREAT_COUNCIL_BODY}	Sire, a great council has been called. Local priests wish to attend. Do you wish to fund this?\n\nIt will cost 1500 Florins, but may aid your priests in attaining spiritual wisdom. Of course declining to fund such may be seen as a lack of piety on your part.
{GREAT_COUNCIL_TITLE}	Great Council
{PIRATES_BODY}	Sire, pirates and brigands have been attacking our trade routes.\n\nWe could fund some privateers to hunt them down for 5000 Florins, or take the risk and hope our trade gets through.
{PIRATES_TITLE}	Trade Routes Attacked
{CAPITAL_CHANGE_BODY}Moving the seat of power to another settlement opens a new chapter in the history. Soon the new Capital will be the place where the majority of the aristocrats live and influence both the ruler, and his council... although there was a temporary disorder in the nation, life is starting to be peaceful once again.\n\nThe new capital, as a shining example of your wisdom, will surely help in governing the country more effectively.
{CAPITAL_CHANGE_TITLE}New Seat of Power
{EARLY_ERA_BODY}for gracul
{EARLY_ERA_TITLE}Early Era
{LATE_ERA_BODY}for gracul
{LATE_ERA_TITLE}Late Era
{SPAIN_UNIFY_BODY}   the Crowns of the Christian kingdoms of Castile and Aragon united to form an Spanish Empire
{SPAIN_UNIFY_TITLE}  Spanish Empire
{THE_WHEELLOCK_BODY}	Wheellock was the next major development in firearms technology after the matchlock and the first self-igniting firearm. The mechanism is so-called because it uses a rotating steel wheel to provide ignition.The invention of the wheellock is sometimes credited to the German Johann Kiefuss of Nuremberg in 1517. However, this is impossible, as Kiefuss lived about 100 years later, and there are many references to wheellocks existing before 1517.
{THE_WHEELLOCK_TITLE}  Wheellock discovery
{THE_MATCHLOCK_BODY}	The Matchlock was the first mechanism or "lock" invented to uncomplicate the firing of a hand-held firearm. This design removed the need to lower a lit match into the flash pan by hand and made it possible to have both hands free to keep a firm grip on the weapon at the moment of firing, and more importantly to keep both eyes on the target.The famous Janissary corps of the Ottoman army were soon using matchlock muskets as early as the 1440s. The matchlock appeared in Europe some time in the mid-1400s, although the idea of the serpentine appears some 40 years previously in an Austrian manuscript. The first dated illustration of a matchlock mechanism dates to 1475, and by the 1500s they were universally used. Despite the appearance of more advanced ignition systems such as that of the wheellock and the snaphance, the low cost of production, simplicity, and high availability of the matchlock kept it in use in European armies until about 1720. It was eventually completely replaced by the flintlock as the foot soldier's main armament.
{THE_MATCHLOCK_TITLE}	Matchlock discovery
{THE_SNAPHANCE_BODY}	A Snaphance or Snaphaunce is another type of mechanism for firing a gun (or a gun using that mechanism).The snaphance first appeared in the late 1550s as a development of the earlier snaplock. The main improvement was that the pan-cover opened automatically (to keep the priming dry until the exact moment of firing), as in the wheel-lock. (The snaplock had a manually operated pan cover similar to that of the matchlock. Some definitions class the snaphaunce as a sub-type of snaplock.) Also like the wheel-lock, the snaphance used a lateral sear mechanism to connect trigger to cock. Later models had a variety of safety mechanisms to prevent accidental discharge of the gun.The snaphance was used from the late 1550s until modern times (in North African guns), but by about 1680 it was out of fashion everywhere except Northern Italy where it persisted until the 1750s. In Europe, and especially France, the snaphance was replaced by the flintlock with its combined steel/pan cover starting from about 1620. In England, a hybrid mechanism called the English Lock replaced the snaphance from the same date. Both the flintlock and the English lock were cheaper and less complex than the snaphance.
{THE_SNAPHANCE_TITLE}	Snaphance discovery
{THE_FLINTLOCK_BODY}	The simple serpentine of the arquebus has been replaced with a more advanced snaphance lock which uses a spring operated trigger or lever to lower the slow match into the priming pan which opens automatically (so keeping the priming dry until the exact moment of firing).  The firearm that utilizes this device is known as a Musket. (c. Mid 16th century)
{THE_FLINTLOCK_TITLE}	Advanced Matchlock
{IMPROVED_METALLURGY_BODY}	Improved metallurgy allows the production of stronger armors, a process is pioneered in the Italian States.
{IMPROVED_METALLURGY_TITLE}	Improved Metallurgy
{ADVANCED_METALLURGY_BODY}	A further improvement in metallurgy allows an increase in protection for some metal armors, though the expense and difficulty of manufacture often means these are only avaialable to the rich initially.
{ADVANCED_METALLURGY_TITLE}	Advanced Metallurgy
{PIKE_AND_SHOT_BODY}	During this period firearms become increasingly effective, while infantry makes greater use of the pike to ward off enemy cavalry and protect the gunners.
{PIKE_AND_SHOT_TITLE}	Pike and Shot

{TROUBADOURS_BODY}	Within Occitania (southern France) troubadours and trobairitz (male and female) performers have stared to appear.  Their songs and poetry deal with all forms chivalry and courtly love and they are proving popular with the ladies in many a court.  William IX, Duke of Aquitaine (or Guilhèm de Peitieus in Occitan) is perhaps the most noted early composer of such works "one of the most courtly men in the world and one of the greatest deceivers of women. He was a fine knight at arms, liberal in his womanizing, and a fine composer and singer of songs. He travelled much through the world, seducing women."
{TROUBADOURS_TITLE}	First Troubadours
{TROUBADOURS_EVENT_BODY}	A famous group of Troubadours wish to perform at your court, do you wish to fund their performance.\n\nDoing so will cost you 1000, but could improve your image as a cultured ruler and inspire any of your princesses who are near the capital.
{TROUBADOURS_EVENT_TITLE}	Troubadours Arrive 
{PANTOKRATOR_BODY}At the behest of the Byzantine Empress Ireni the Pantokrator monastery has been built in Constantinople. Within its walls there lies a most beautiful church, richly decorated with mosaics and rare marbles, the most modern hospital in Europe with a staff of 50, and a mausoleum dedicated to St. Michael the Archangel, where many of the great Emperors will be laid to rest.
{PANTOKRATOR_TITLE}Pantokrator
{ALBIGENSIAN_HERESY_BODY}	The Albigensian heresy which has been practiced in the Languedoc region of southern France since 1012, having probarly come by trade routes from eastern Europe, has finally come to a head, with the Pope calling for them to be eradicated. Cathars, as they are known by their opponents, are a anti-sacerdotal party in permanent opposition to the Roman church, and protest against the corruption of the clergy. The nobles and people of the region have strongly supported this heresy and even held a synod of heretics including Bogumils from Bulgaria, the Balkans and northern Italy at St Felix de Caraman, near Toulouse.  upon hearing this the people of southern France have raised up in defence of there religon under the leadership of Raymond VI, count of Toulouse.
{ALBIGENSIAN_HERESY_TITLE}Albigensian Heresy
{SWISS_LEAGUE_BODY}Surrounded by greedy enemies who seek to control important trade routes and vulnerable in the Empire's constant struggles, the three Swiss Forest cantons of Uri, Schwyz and Unterwalden have signed a oath of fellowship or Eidgenossenschaft pledging mutual aid against all enemies. Although a small start, this confederation of Swiss cantons has sharp teeth: the pikes in the hands of its many soldiers!
{SWISS_LEAGUE_TITLE}The Everlasting League
{SHATIR_BODY}Ibn al-Shatir, the great Arabic Muslim astronomer, mathematician, engineer and inventor has died. His work 'The Final Quest Concerning the Rectification of Principles' set the founding principles for later western astronomer, he invented the first astrolabic clock, a compass dial, and the concept of splitting the hours of the day into equal lengths, which he incoporated into a magnificent sundial. 
{SHATIR_TITLE}Ibn al-Shatir Dies

{CONCENTRIC_CASTLES_BODY}Fortifications design has entered a new era with the building of castles based on a concentric design. Unlike older square keep castles, concentric castles had no central keep, but a very heavily defended entrance and the central core being defended by a series of curtain walls. The outer curtain wall has the smallest height, while the inner curtain wall nearest to the castle being the highest, so giving the defenders the maximum advantage over those attempting to take over the castle.
{CONCENTRIC_CASTLES_TITLE}Concentric Castles

{HEAVY_MAIL_ARMOR_BODY}New techniques in production of mail have reduced their cost and now full body suits of mail armour are common. (c. 13th century)
{HEAVY_MAIL_ARMOR_TITLE}Heavy Mail

{HALF_PLATE_ARMOR_BODY}Coverage of metal plates increases, with mail often now used only to protect vulnerable joints. (c. 14th century)
{HALF_PLATE_ARMOR_TITLE}Partial Plate Armor

{TRANSITIONAL_ARMOR_BODY}Single plates of metal armour are now being worn over a full mail haubergeon in order to protect vulnerable areas. (c. Mid 13th century)
{TRANSITIONAL_ARMOR_TITLE}Coat of Plates

{PAVISE_SHIELDS_BODY}The use of a large oblong convex shield, said to be designed in the northern Italian city of Pavia is becoming popular. Used mainly by archers and crossbowmen to protect themselves from enemy fire (especially during sieges). A typical feature is a central groove on the inside to hold a stake that can inserted in the ground to act as a prop (c. 14th century)
{PAVISE_SHIELDS_TITLE}Pavise Shields

{FULL_PLATE_ARMOR_BODY}Larger and complete full plates of armour had been developed. Many of them are masterpieces of workmanship and design. (c. Late 14th century)
{FULL_PLATE_ARMOR_TITLE}Full Plate Armor

{GOTHIC_ARMOR_BODY}New designs for plate armor include new helmet and neckguard designs. Many of these new armours are masterpieces of workmanship and refinement. Examples of these different styles can be found made by the Italians of Milan, English of Greenwich, Serbians of Novo Brdo and Kotor, and of course in southern Germany (especially in Nuremberg) where the style is called Gothic.(c. Early 15th century)
{GOTHIC_ARMOR_TITLE}Gothic Plate Armor

{MOUNTED_CROSSBOWS_BODY}The pushlever and ratchet drawing mechanisms has been invented, leading to the development of new cavalry tactics and the introduction of the mounted crossbowman. (c. 13th century)
{MOUNTED_CROSSBOWS_TITLE}Mounted Crossbows developed

{ENGLISH_ARCHERS_BODY}The English have made the practice of the Longbow compulsory, banning all sports but archery on Sundays. This has ensured that thier king can call upon a large pool of expert archers and provides them with an edge in military battles to come. 
{ENGLISH_ARCHERS_TITLE}English Archers

{CANNONS_BODY}These instruments which discharge balls of metal with most tremendous noise and flashes of fire are viewed with greatest astonishment and admiration. (c. 1324 AD)
{CANNONS_TITLE}Cannons Developed

{HANDGUN_BODY}Early handguns are short and stocky with a barrel length of 165mm and a bore of 15mm.  Manufactures soon learn though that an increased barrel length allows the gunpowder to completely burn before the bullet leaves the muzzle, and guns become about 375mm in length with a bore of 21mm.   Such weapons have no true stock, but are set on a wooden stave which is held under the arms while a smouldering match or hot wire is applied to the vent. (c. late 14th century).  Later versions use a stock and a simple matchlock firing mechanism called a serpentine,  
{HANDGUN_TITLE}Handgun Developed

{MATCHLOCK_BODY}A simple matchlock is a device called a serpentine which was essentially an "S" shaped piece of metal with a central pivot attached to the side of the gun. By pulling on the bottom half of the pivot you lowered the upper half, which held a burning slow match (hemp or cotton rope soaked in saltpetre) into a pan containing a priming charge of powder to fire the gun. This allows the shooter to place the weapon on his shoulder and use both hands to aim, while allowing him to concentrate on firing, rather than a match. The firearm that utilizes this device is known as the Arquebus. (c. Mid 15th century)  A variety of matchlock was also developed called the snapping matchlock, in which the serpentine was strongly spring-loaded, and released by pressing a button, pulling a trigger, or pulling a short string passing into the mechanism. As the match was often extinguished after its relatively violent collision with the flash pan, this type fell out of favour with soldiers, but is often used in fine target weapons.
{MATCHLOCK_TITLE}Matchlock Developed

{ADV_MATCHLOCK_BODY}The number of firearms in European armies begins to rise, while those who had previously dismissed the weapon are forced to re-evaluate their decision to ignore it in favour of shock and cold steel.
{ADV_MATCHLOCK_TITLE}The Rise of Shot	 

{MUSKET_INVENTED_BODY}The first muskets were developments of the arquebus, using a heavier load of powder and shot to greater range and to greater effect. The weapon was heavy however, requiring a strong man and good training to use effectively.
{MUSKET_INVENTED_TITLE}Musket Developed
{BULGARIAN_UPRISING_BODY}Tired of having to pay taxes to foreign rulers, the Bulgars and Vlachs have revolted. They have taken up arms and have laid siege to the settlements they consider to be rightfully theirs!
{BULGARIAN_UPRISING_TITLE}Rebellion in Bulgaria!

{LITHUANIA_KING_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late Lithuanian ruler, his heir has succeeded to the throne. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...	
{LITHUANIA_KING_EVENT_TITLE}The Lithuanian Duke is dead!	
{LITHUANIA_REGENT_EVENT_BODY}With the death of the late Lithuanian ruler, a regent has been selected to administer the realm. The Royal Houses know not whether to find fear or comfort in this knowledge...	
{LITHUANIA_REGENT_EVENT_TITLE}End of a Dynasty?	

{PALANGA_RENAME_BODY}Königsberg has been founded on the site of the ancient Old Prussian settlement of Twangste by the Teutonic Knights, the literal meaning of its name is'King's Mountain', gifted with a port to the Baltic sea this settlement has potential to develop in a prosperous and successful merchant center.
{PALANGA_RENAME_TITLE}Königsberg Founded 
