¬ ---------- Faction Intros Subtitles ---------------------
¬ ---------- Exported from MTW2_Speech.xls ----------------
¬ ---------------- English ----------------------

{Mongols_Invade_2}
To discount the menaces that lurk beyond the known world is to risk a rude awakening that can become a nightmare.

{Mongols_Invade_3}
This nightmare is the Mongol invasion.

{Britannia_Wallace_Emerges_1}
The Fires of Independence burn brightly in Scotland.

{Britannia_Wallace_Emerges_2}
Weary of  aggression from it's neighbours, a new hero has emerged to unite Scotland's clans.

{Britannia_Wallace_Emerges_3}
His name is William Wallace.  

{Britannia_Wallace_Emerges_4}
A minor noble he may be, but behind him marches thousands of warriors.

{Britannia_Wallace_Emerges_5}
Each one with freedom in his heart and a sword in his hand.

{Crusades_Christians_take_Jerusalem_1}
By the Grace of God, those who went forth in the name our Lord have captured Jerusalem. 

{Crusades_Christians_take_Jerusalem_2}
Thus the Holy city has been triumphantly reclaimed in the name of Christ.

{Crusades_Christians_take_Jerusalem_3}
All of Christendom will rejoice, for God's Children may now find salvation in the Kingdom of Heaven.

{Crusades_Muslims_take_Jerusalem_1}
Today the followers of the Prophet Mohammed rejoice. 

{Crusades_Muslims_take_Jerusalem_2}
For Muslim armies have captured the Holy city of Jerusalem.

{Crusades_3rd_Crusade_arrives_1}
Heeding the call of Christendom.

{Crusades_3rd_Crusade_arrives_2}
Two of Europe’s greatest Kings, Richard I of England and Phillip II of France have arrived in the Holy Land,

{Crusades_3rd_Crusade_arrives_3}
Ready to lead the 3rd Crusade to glory, and help restore the Kingdom of Heaven.

{Britannia_Edward_Returns_1}
After a successful crusade in the holy lands, Edward returns home a hero.

{Britannia_Edward_Returns_2}
Battle hardened and with Templar forces in tow,

{Britannia_Edward_Returns_3}
the English people rejoice…

{Britannia_Edward_Returns_4}
...believing Edward can only  lead them to further victories, 

{Britannia_Edward_Returns_5}
as he now turns his attention to conflict closer to home.

{Teutonic_Lithuania_Converts_1}
Christendom rejoices! The mother Church has gained a new sheep to the fold. 

{Teutonic_Lithuania_Converts_2}
The people of Lithuania have agreed to put aside their Pagan ways and embrace the holy word of Christ.

{Teutonic_Kalmar_Union_1}
The people of Norway have united with their Danish neighbours under one banner and ruler, to form what is being called the Kalmar Union. Nowadays to raise a fist at one is to raise a fist to all in the Union.


{Americas_England_And_France_Arrive_1}
Europe is afire with tales from the New World. 

{Americas_England_And_France_Arrive_2}
Rumours of cities made of gold and people covered in jewels, draws others to this strange new land.

{Americas_England_And_France_Arrive_3}
Even now, foreign fleets make their way across the sea.

{Americas_Native_American_Warpath_Called_1}
The fire of anger has been lit amongst the Apachean Tribes. 

{Americas_Native_American_Warpath_Called_2}
A warpath has been called and only the blood of the tribes’ enemies will soothe the Great Spirit.

{Americas_Native_American_Warpath_Called_3}
Beware all; these people  bring forth a storm of fury and vengeance.

{Americas_Spanish_New_Expedition_Arrives_1}
Ever hungry for more gold and fresh conquests, Spain sends another expedition to the New World.

{Americas_Spanish_New_Expedition_Arrives_2}
Wherever the cities of Gold lie, these men, God willing, will find them.

{British_Isles_Narrator_1}
Britannia, a land of emerald Isles, a land of kings, a land of war.

{British_Isles_Narrator_2}
England…King Henry sits upon a hungry throne thirsty for more land.

{British_Isles_Narrator_3}
The Norwegians,… warriors happy to pay the blood price for their ambitions.

{British_Isles_Narrator_4}
Scotland, from the highlands and across the lowlands comes a spirited people ready for battle.

{British_Isles_Narrator_5}
Wales, …a people of song and sword, and leaders that will bend their knees to no man.


{British_Isles_Narrator_6}
And Ireland, suspicious of his neighbours, the Irish warrior never sleeps, though he dreams of conquest.

{British_Isles_Narrator_7}
Britannia……One realm,…  5 Kings… TOTAL WAR.

{Crusades_Narrator_1}
The Holy Lands, Outremer, a land of faith, a land of war.

{Crusades_Narrator_2}
Byzantium, the majestic gateway to the East and the Crusades.



{Crusades_Narrator_3}
The Principality of Antioch, a proud Crusader State and home to the Hospitallers.

{Crusades_Narrator_4}
Jerusalem, the Holy City, a Kingdom forged by blood, steel and faith. A place revered by the faithful and coveted by many.

{Crusades_Narrator_5}
In the East the mighty Seljuks, led by Nur-ed-Din, fighting to drive the accursed Crusaders into the Sea.

{Crusades_Narrator_6}
And to the South rises the cunning Salah al-Din, builder of an empire, an Empire ready to grind the Crusaders into the desert sands.



{Crusades_Narrator_7}
This is a time of faith,

{Crusades_Narrator_8}
a time of battle,

{Crusades_Narrator_9}
a time of Total War.

{Teutonic_Narrator_1}
The brooding forests of the Baltic, home to the old Gods, now home to war.

{Teutonic_Narrator_2}
The ruthless Knights of the Teutonic Order, who came to deal with Pagan Lithuania at Poland's request, now carve a bloody swathe across the land.

{Teutonic_Narrator_3}
The Lithuanian Pagans fight with grim determination. Yet the path of the Holy Cross may be inevitable.

{Teutonic_Narrator_4}
Surrounding this bloody conflict, sleeping giants, begin to stir.

{Teutonic_Narrator_5}
Novgorod, a powerful Republic, jealously guarding its freedom and trade.

{Teutonic_Narrator_6}
The mighty Danes, renowned as seafarers and warriors, willing to back their ambitions with brute force.

{Teutonic_Narrator_7}
And of course Poland, a proud Kingdom, once allied to the Teutonic knights, Now battered and regretful; must face the demons it unleashed.

{Teutonic_Narrator_8}
Ambition…

{Teutonic_Narrator_9}
Greed…

{Teutonic_Narrator_10}
Faith…

{Teutonic_Narrator_11}
Total War!

{The_Americas_Narrator_1}
Speak of the New World and men dream of riches, glory and conquest.

{The_Americas_Narrator_2}
This land is home to the fearsome and decadent Aztecs. A people who appease their great Sungod with hearts torn from the chests of their enemies  ...and enemies the Aztecs have a' plenty.

{The_Americas_Narrator_3}
To the East on the Yucatan Peninsula, the Mayans, a majestic people with an epic history dream of restoring their once great Empire to it former glory.

{The_Americas_Narrator_4}
North, beyond the jungles, roam the Apachaen tribes, skilled hunters who follow the great herds across the plains and fearsome warriors who are quick to learn the ways of their enemies.

{The_Americas_Narrator_5}
A new enemy sails on the horizon, bearing steel and marching under the Holy Cross. To Spain the New World is a land of hope, a land where the Holy Word is delivered on the end of a sword. 

{The_Americas_Narrator_6}
A land where empires are born.

{The_Americas_Narrator_7}
A land of Total War.

{Americas_Apachean_Outro_Win_1}
The Apachean warriors are an implacable foe. On the plains and in the deep forrests these mighty warriors crushed both Christians and Heathens. The New World is their domain and they are its rulers.

{Americas_Apachean_Outro_Lose_1}
The Apachean people have been crushed and scattered to the four winds. They lacked neither fearsome warriors nor bravery. 

{Americas_Apachean_Outro_Lose_2}
It seems their leaders were found wanting and as usual it is the people that pay the price.

{Americas_Meso_American_Outro_Win_1}
The warriors of the New World are fierce and fearless. It is little wonder then that they crushed both Christians and Heathens. The New World is their realm and they are its kings.

{Americas_Meso_American_Outro_Lose_1}
The heathens of the New World, though fierce and fearless, have tasted bitter defeat. Crushed by their enemies, they lie scattered and frightened. Their beastly empire with its bloody sacrifices naught but ashes.

{Americas_Spanish_Outro_Win_1}
Spain sent her sons to the New World seeking lands, and conquest. Enduring struggles and hazards that would have tested the bravest souls, Spain’s brave conquistadors have ushered in a New Age and won undying fame.

{Americas_Spanish_Outro_Lose_1}
The Spanish came to the New World with conquest in their eyes. Yet with all their skill at the arts of war and faith in Christ, they gained naught but death and disgrace; betrayed by leadership whose only quality was foolishness.

{Crusades_Muslim_Outro_Win_1}
The followers of Mohammed have claimed the Holy Lands as their own. Though the Crusaders fought tooth and nail to forge a Kingdom of Heaven, the warriors of the East prevailed, and it is the Crescent that shines above Jerusalem tonight.

{Crusades_Muslim_Outro_Lose_1}
The followers of Mohammed, though brave in battle, and faithful in their own manner, have lost control of the Holy Lands. From accounts one hears from returning pilgrims, it appears a weakness of leadership has earned them this fate.

{Americas_Kingdoms_Game_Intro_1}
War... It was no stranger to the people of the New World.

{Americas_Kingdoms_Game_Intro_2}
Blood and death were always a part of life in these heathen lands.

{Americas_Kingdoms_Game_Intro_3}
But when the Old World arrived from across the seas...

{Americas_Kingdoms_Game_Intro_4}
It would clash with the New in a war that would forever change the Americas.

{Britannia_Kingdoms_Game_Intro_1}
War… It has always been a part of life in the British Isles.

{Britannia_Kingdoms_Game_Intro_2}
From Roman times unto present day, no King or Emperor has called this realm his own.

{Britannia_Kingdoms_Game_Intro_3}
Five kings now stand ready to do battle over these lands.

{Britannia_Kingdoms_Game_Intro_4}
They will make Britannia theirs... Or die in the attempt!

{Crusades_Kingdoms_Game_Intro_1}
War... It is no stranger to men of faith…

{Crusades_Kingdoms_Game_Intro_2}
who are driven to fight with a fury no King or Sultan can inspire.

{Crusades_Kingdoms_Game_Intro_3}
From across the sands and the seas.. they fight for the Holy Lands..

{Crusades_Kingdoms_Game_Intro_4}
To ensure the hell that is their lives, will grant their passage into heaven.

{Teutonic_Kingdoms_Game_Intro_1}
War... A scourge that breaks out wherever different faiths meet.

{Teutonic_Kingdoms_Game_Intro_2}
Being the last of the Pagan kingdoms Lithuania faces a bloody destiny.

{Teutonic_Kingdoms_Game_Intro_3}
Hunted by the Teutonic Knights, they must give up their false gods...

{Teutonic_Kingdoms_Game_Intro_4}
Or they must risk giving up their lives instead, in an ungodly war!

